Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection1874-1961 (bulk 1910-1961)
ML31.G8
Gunn, Glenn Dillard, 1874-1963
circa 750 items 14 boxes 4.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Primarily correspondence from, among others, Ferruccio Busoni, Teresa Careño, Percy Grainger, and Moriz Rosenthal. Also photographs, many with autograph inscriptions including those of Claude Debussy, Victor Herbert, and John McCormack. Music is represented by manuscripts and autographed presentation scores (printed). The ramainder consists of miscellaneous personal papers, programs, and clippings.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Busoni, Ferruccio, 1866-1924--Correspondence.; Busoni, Ferruccio, 1866-1924.; Carreño, Teresa, 1853-1917--Correspondence.; Carreño, Teresa, 1853-1917.; Debussy, Claude, 1862-1918.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961--Correspondence.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961.; Gunn, Glenn Dillard, 1874-1963.; Gunn, Glenn Dillard, 1874-1963.; Herbert, Victor, 1859-1924.; McCormack, John, 1884-1945.; Rosenthal, Moriz, 1862-1946--Correspondence.; Rosenthal, Moriz, 1862-1946.
Subjects
Composers--Autographs.; Musicians--Correspondence.; Musicians--Photographs.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Given to the Library by Gunn's daughters, Janet Gunn McLean and Nancy Stephens in 1971.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Glenn Dillard Gunn, 1874-1963, music critic and pianist; music critic of Chicago tribune, Chicago herald examiner, and Washington times-herald.
Scope and Content Note
The Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection consists primarily of Correspondence, Photographs, and Music. The range of dates represented in the collection is 1874-1961.
Worthy of note in the collection are letters from correspondents such as Ferruccio Busoni, Teresa Carreño, Percy Grainger, and Moriz Rosenthal. There are also numerous photographs with autograph inscriptions to the Gunns, including those of Claude Debussy, Victor Herbert, and John McCormack. The sizable collection of printed music includes a number of autographed presentation scores, such as Eric Delamarter's Suite from The Black Orchid and Symphony no. 3, and Moriz Rosenthal's Zehn CharakterStücke. The manuscript music in Gunn's own hand consists of an arrangement of J. S. Bach's English Suite no. 3 for winds and a transcription of a Bach keyboard concerto for three pianos. A manuscript of several songs from the Gitanjali cycle by John Alden Carpenter, though in the hand of a copyist, does include Carpenter's own pencilled indications of orchestration.
The remainder of the collection consists of miscellaneous personal papers, programs and clippings.
Claudia Widgery, October 1992
Organization of the Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection
The Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection is organized in 7 series:
Writings of Glenn Dillard Gunn
Correspondence
Personal Papers
Programs & Announcements
Clippings
Photographs
Music
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010563510
Container List
- Writings of Glenn Dillard Gunn (Box 1)
  Articles for the All-American Youth Orchestra (1940), a Diary, a letter to Lucy Furman (1955), and an undated typescript article.
  Arrangement is by date.
  - Articles for series on the Leopold Stokowski All-American Youth Orchestra tour of South America, July 31 - September 4, 1940, arranged chronologically (typescript drafts) See also: CLIPPINGS (Box 1)
  - Diary / Account book, 1893-1897 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Lucy Furman ("Cousin Pearl"), dated June 28, 1955 (Box 1)
  - "The Spirit of Chopin: An Article" (typescript) (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  Letters to Glenn Dillard Gunn. The bulk date of these letters is from 1949-1955.
  Alphabetically arranged by correspondent.
  - Albert, Eugène d' (Box 1)
  - Allen, Lyman Whitney (Box 1)
  - American University (Box 1)
  - Armitage, Albert (Box 1)
  - Beesley, Thomas Quinn (Box 1)
  - Borowski, Felix (Box 1)
  - Bos, Coenraad V. (Box 1)
  - Busoni, Ferruccio, Also: Mrs. Busoni (Box 1)
  - Cain, Mrs. James M. see: Macbeth, Florence
  - Carreño, Teresa (Box 1)
  - Chicago Symphony Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Cliff Dwellers Club, Chicago (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Susan (Box 1)
  - Damrosch, Walter (Box 1)
  - Garden, Mary (Box 1)
  - Garland, Hamlin (Box 1)
  - Göhler, Georg (Box 1)
  - Gorudnitzki, Sascha (Box 1)
  - Grainger, Percy (Box 1)
  - Gretchaninoff, Marie (Box 1)
  - Gunn family (Box 1)
  - Higgins, May (Box 1)
  - Hinze-Reinhold, Bruno (Box 1)
  - Imaz, Betty (Box 1)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary of America (Box 1)
  - Johansen, Gunnar (Box 1)
  - Kindler, Hans (Box 1)
  - Klein, Arthur G. (Box 1)
  - Kozeluch, Thaddeus (Box 1)
  - Leidzen, Erik (Box 1)
  - Luoma, R. (Box 1)
  - Macbeth, Florence (Box 1)
  - MacMillen, Francis (Box 1)
  - Marsh, Mary Drew (Box 1)
  - Mitropoulos, Dimitri (Box 1)
  - Moore, Helen (Box 1)
  - Musical Courier (Box 1)
  - Nielsen, Alice (Box 1)
  - Nies-Berger, Edouard (Box 1)
  - Novaes, Guiomar (Box 1)
  - Parker, H. T. (Box 1)
  - Patterson, Eleanor (Box 1)
  - Philadelphia Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Prokofieff, Serge (Box 1)
  - Rosenthal, Moriz (Box 1)
  - Samaroff, Olga (Box 1)
  - Schein, Ann (Box 1)
  - Schiffeler, Curt C. (Box 1)
  - Schulhof, Andrew (Box 1)
  - Schumann-Heink, Ernestine (Box 1)
  - Shepherd, Arthur (Box 1)
  - Skinner, Ernest M. (Box 1)
  - Somach, Beverly (Box 1)
  - Stokowski, Leopold (Box 1)
  - Tagliapietra, A. (Box 1)
  - Taylor, Deems (Box 1)
  - Teichmüller, Robert (Box 1)
  - Thalberg, Germaine (Box 1)
  - Thalberg, Marcian (Box 1)
  - United States White House (Box 1)
  - University of Rochester (Box 1)
  - Unschuld, Marie von (Box 1)
  - Vose, Samuel N. (Box 1)
  - Wright, Nellie Burt (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Personal Papers (Box 2)
  Miscellaneous personal documents (including school report card, temperance pledges, church tribute, etc.).
  Arrangement is alphabetical by general description of each item.
  - Miscellaneous personal documents (including school report card, temperance pledges, church tribute, etc.) (Box 2)
- Programs & Announcements (Box 2)
  Various programs and announcements from 1874-1943.
  Arrangement is by genre and then by date.
  - Programs and announcements (1906-1943, undated) (Box 2)
  - Programmes for the Summer Season, 1874 [by] Theodore Thomas. [Bound volume given by Thomas to Milman Adams on March 12th, 1883; given by Adams to Glenn Dillard Gunn on May 12, 1910] (Box 2)
- Clippings (Box 2)
  Reviews and articles written by Gunn dated from 1902-1940.
  - Reviews by Gunn and press notices on recitals and lectures, 1902- (in bound scrapbook) (Box 2)
  - Reviews and articles by Gunn, 1905 (in 3-ring notebook) (Box 2)
  - Reviews written by Gunn (unbound) (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Gunn's performances written by others (Box 2)
  - Series of articles by Gunn on the Leopold Stokowski All-American Youth Orchestra tour of South America (1940) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs (Box 3)
  Photographs taken of Glenn Dillard and others. Many of these photographs have inscriptions to Gunn, his wife (Bernya Bracken Gunn) or his daughter (Janet Gunn).
  Arrangement is alphabetically by name.
  - Photographs of Glenn Dillard Gunn (Box 3)
    - Glenn Dillard Gunn (Box 3)
    - Glenn Dillard Gunn with others (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Others (Box 3)
    - Anderson, Marian (Box 3)
    - Bach, Johann Sebastian, photo of portrait owned by William F. Scheide (Box 3)
    - Barer, Simon (Box 3)
    - Bauer, Harold (Box 3)
    - Bispham, David (Box 3)
    - Busoni, Ferruccio (Box 3)
    - Caruso, Enrico (Box 3)
    - Chaliapin, Feodor (Box 3)
    - Chopin, Frédéric (Box 3)
    - Debussy, Claude (Box 3)
    - Devries, Herman (Box 3)
    - Dupré, Marcel (Box 3)
    - Flagstad, Kirsten (Box 3)
    - Frantz, Dalies (Box 3)
    - Freund, Etelka (Box 3)
    - Friedheim, Arthur (Box 3)
    - Gadski, Johanna (Box 3)
    - Gallo, Fortune (Box 3)
    - Garden, Mary (Box 3)
    - Gieseking, Walter (Box 3)
    - Gradova, Gitta (Box 3)
    - Heifetz, Jascha (Box 3)
    - Herbert, Victor (Box 3)
    - Hofmann, Josef (Box 3)
    - Jepson, Helen (Box 3)
    - Kreisler, Fritz (Box 3)
    - Kurenko, Maria (Box 3)
    - Lhevinne, Josef (Box 3)
    - Liszt, Franz (Box 3)
    - Mason, Edith (Box 3)
    - McCormack, John (Box 3)
    - Menuhin, Yehudi (Box 3)
    - Middleschulte, Wilhelm (Box 3)
    - Milstein, Nathan (Box 3)
    - Mordkin, Michel (Box 3)
    - Neill, Amy (Box 3)
    - Nielson, Alice (Box 3)
    - Novaes, Guiomar (Box 3)
    - Petrillo, C. (Box 3)
    - Piatigorsky, Gregor (Box 3)
    - Pinto, Mrs. Octavio see: Novaes, Guiomar
    - Polacco, Giorgio (Box 3)
    - Polacco, Mrs. Giorgio see: Mason, Edith
    - Rachmaninoff, Sergei (Box 3)
    - Rodzinski, Artur (Box 3)
    - Rosenthal, Moriz (Box 3)
    - Saint-Saëns, Camille (Box 3)
    - Samaroff-Stokowski, Olga (Box 3)
    - Schein, Ann (Box 3)
    - Schumann-Heink, Ernestine (Box 3)
    - Spalding, Albert (Box 3)
    - Stock, Frederick A. (Box 3)
    - Szigeti, Joseph (Box 3)
    - Tauscher, Mrs. Hans see: Gadski, Johanna
    - Teichmuller, Robert (Box 3)
    - Templeton, Alex (Alec) (Box 3)
    - Thomas, John Charles (Box 3)
    - Toscanini, Arturo (Box 3)
    - Wettergren, Gertrud (Box 3)
    - Zeisler, Fannie Bloomfield (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - locations (Box 3)
- Music (Box 4-14)
  The Music series is represented by two subseries. The first subseries is Manuscript music collected by Glenn Dillard Gunn. The second subseries is Printed music collected by Glenn Dillard Gunn.
  Arrangement is genre, composer or arranger and title.
  - Manuscript music (Box 4)
    - Bach, Johann Sebastian
      - English suite in G minor, Arranged by Glenn Dillard Gunn for wind choir. (Box 4)
      - Konzert für Orchester, no. 3, BWV 1064., Arranged by Glenn Dillard Gunn for three pianos. (Box 4)
    - Carpenter, John Alden
      - Gitanjali, no. 57, 60-62, 80, 90, Note: in copyist's hand, with Carpenter's pencilled indications of orchestration (Box 4)
    - Gunn, Glenn Dillard
      - [Miscellaneous fragments] (Box 4)
  - Printed music (Box 4-14)
    - Piano, 2 hands (Box 4-6)
      - Bach, Carl Philipp Emanuel
        - Solfeggietto (Box 4)
      - Beethoven, Ludwig van
        - Andante in F major, Arranged by Immanuel von Faisst, rev. by Sigmund Lebert. (Box 4)
        - Eccossaisen, Arranged by Ferruccio B. Busoni. (Box 4)
        - Sonata, op. 14, no. 2, Arranged by Immanuel von Faisst, rev. by Sigmund Lebert. (Box 4)
        - Sonate, Edited by Alfredo Casella. (Box 4)
        - Sonate, Edited by Louis Köhler. (Box 5)
      - Brahms, Johannes
        - Zwei Rhapsodien. (Box 5)
      - Busoni, Ferruccio
        - Elegien, [incomplete] (Box 5)
      - Carpenter, John Alden
        - Polonaise américaine (Box 5)
      - Carreño, Teresa
        - Kleiner Walzer (Box 5)
      - Chopin, Frédéric
        - Etuden, Edited by Herrmann Scholtz. (Box 5)
      - Clementi, Muzio
        - Gradus ad Parnassum, Edited by Carl Tausig. (Box 5)
      - Crawford, Caroline H.
        - Sur la glace à Sweet Briar (Box 5)
      - Debussy, Claude
        - Estampes (Box 5)
      - Fernândez, Lorenzo
        - Moda (Box 5)
      - Godard, Benjamin
        - Au matin (Box 5)
      - Godowsky, Leopold
        - Suite for the left hand alone (Box 5)
      - Goodell, Walter
        - Six original piano solos in classic style (Box 6)
      - Granados, E.
        - Goyescas (Box 6)
      - Green, Ray
        - Festival fugues, an American toccata, Note: blueprint copy of holograph (Box 6)
      - Grieg, Edvard
        - Lyrische Stücke, Heft II. Morceaux lyricques, op. 38. (Box 6)
      - Liszt, Franz
        - Années de Pèlerinage: 1ère année: Suisse: V. Orages. (Box 6)
        - Apparition no. 2 (Box 6)
        - Etüden, Edited by the Franz Liszt Stiftung [autographed by Ferruccio Busoni]. (Box 6)
        - Gnomenreigen (Box 6)
        - Rhapsodies hongroises (Box 6)
        - Grandes études de Paganini, Transcribed for piano. (Box 6)
        - Soirées de Vienne, no. 6, A piece by Franz Liszt in which he adapted 2 or more Schubert's dances. (Box 6)
      - MacDowell, Edward A.
        - 4th Sonata (Keltic) (Box 6)
      - Mason, Rose d'Amore
        - Five short pieces for children, Note: autographed. (Box 6)
      - Phillips, Honor
        - The Kingly Classics, Edited by Maisie Aldridge (Box 4)
      - Pinto, Octavio
        - Marcha do Pequeno Polegar, Note: autographed. (Box 6)
      - Rachmaninoff, Serge
        - Neuf études-tableaux, op. 39, no. 3, 5. (Box 6)
        - Prélude, op. 23, no. 9. (Box 6)
        - Prélude, op. 32, no. 10. (Box 6)
      - Rameau, Jean Phillippe
        - Rigaudon, Arranged by Leopold Godowsky. (Box 6)
        - Sarabande, Arranged by Leopold Godowsky. (Box 6)
      - Ravel, Maurice
        - Gaspard de la nuit (Box 6)
        - Pièce en forme de habanera. (Box 6)
      - Rosenthal, Moriz
        - Zehn Charakterstücke, Note: autographed. (Box 6)
      - Rubinstein, Anton
        - Barcarolle (Box 6)
      - Schubert, Franz
        - Militär Marsch, Arranged by Carl Tausig. (Box 6)
      - Schumann, Robert
        - Liebeslied, Transcribed by Franz Liszt. (Box 6)
        - Siciliana, op. 68, no. 11 (Box 6)
      - Stevens, Everett
        - Winter starlight, Note: autographed. (Box 6)
    - Piano, 4 hands (Box 7)
      - Albéniz, Isaac
        - Catalonia (Box 7)
      - Debussy, Claude
        - Gigues. Images pour orchestre, no. 1 (Box 7)
        - La mer (Box 7)
      - Ibert, Jacques
        - Escales (Box 7)
      - MacDowell, Edward A.
        - Suite für grosses Orchester, op. 42 (Box 7)
      - Ravel, Maurice
        - Rapsodie espagnole (Box 7)
      - Saint-Saëns, Camille
        - Le carnaval des animaux (Box 7)
      - Schmitt, Florent
        - Une semaine du petit elfe ferme-l'oeil (Box 7)
      - Weber, Carl Maria von
        - Sämtliche Ouvertüren, Note: incomplete. (Box 7)
    - Two pianos (Box 8-9)
      - Bach, Carl Philipp Emanuel
        - Rondo, Arranged by Johannes Doebber. (Box 8)
      - Bach, Johann Sebastian
        - D-moll Konzert, Arranged by Adolf Ruthardt. (Box 8)
        - Konzert für 3 Klaviere in C dur. (Box 8)
      - Bacon, Ernst
        - The burr frolic (Box 8)
      - Beethoven, Ludwig van
        - [Concertos, piano, no. 2, op. 19, B-flat major; arr.], Arranged by Franz Kullak. (Box 8)
        - [Concertos, piano, no. 3, op. 37, C minor; arr.], Arranged by Ch. v. Alkan. (Box 8)
      - Chaminade, C.
        - Deux pièces pour orchestre, op. 79. (Box 8)
      - Chopin, Frédéric
        - Concert für Pianoforte, op. 21, Arranged by Ed. Mertke. (Box 8)
        - Sonaten, Rondos und Variationen, Arranged by Ed. Mertke.; [bound with] Concert für Pianoforte, op. 11. Arranged by Ed. Mertke. (Box 8)
      - Debussy, Claude
        - Nocturnes, Arranged by Maurice Ravel. (Box 8)
      - Frank, César
        - Les Eolides (Box 8)
        - Pièce héroique. (Box 8)
        - Variations symphoniques, Note: incomplete. (Box 9)
      - Liszt, Franz
        - Ungarische fantasie, Arranged by Moriz Rosenthal. (Box 9)
      - MacDowell, Edward A.
        - Erstes Konzert, op. 15 (Box 9)
      - Mendelssohn, Félix
        - Capriccio brillant, op. 22 (Box 9)
        - Rondo brillant, op. 29 (Box 9)
      - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus
        - Claviersonaten, Arranged by Edvard Grieg. (Box 9)
        - Konzert in B dur, Arranged by Bruno Hinze-Reinhold. (Box 9)
      - Paderewski, Ignace Jan
        - Concerto, op. 17 (Box 9)
      - Prokofieff, Serge
        - Troisième concerto, op. 26 (Box 9)
      - Saint-Saëns, Camille
        - Deuxième concert, op. 22 (Box 9)
        - Variations sur un thème de Beethoven, op. 35 (Box 9)
      - Schubert, Franz
        - Symphonie, B minor (Box 9)
      - Schumann, Robert
        - Concerto, op. 54 (Box 9)
      - Weber, Carl Maria von
        - Concertstücke, op. 79 (Box 9)
    - Orchestra - Full score (Box 10-11)
      - Bach, Johann Sebastian
        - Concerto a due cembali, C minor (Box 10)
      - Beethoven, Ludwig van
        - [Concerto, piano, no. 3, op. 37, C minor] (Box 10)
        - [Concerto, piano, no. 5, op. 73, E-flat major] (Box 10)
        - Symphony, no. 1, op. 21, Note: string parts only.; Note: formerly owned by Theodore Thomas. (Box 10)
        - Symphony, no. 2, op. 36, Note: full score, v. 1, vc., bs. parts; Note: formerly owned by Theodore Thomas. (Box 10)
      - Brahms, Johannes
        - Symphony no. 2, op. 73 (Box 10)
      - Delamarter, Eric
        - Suite from The black orchid, Note: autographed. (Box 11)
        - Symphony, no. 3, E minor, Note: autographed. (Box 11)
      - Dvořák, Antonin
        - Symphony, no. 5, E minor, op. 95 (Box 11)
      - Liszt, Franz
        - [Concerto, piano, no. 1] (Box 11)
        - Zweite ungarische Rhapsodie, Edited by Karl Müller-Berghaus. (Box 11)
      - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus
        - [Concerto, piano, no. 10, E-flat major, K. 365] (Box 11)
      - Schumann, Robert
        - Symphony, no. 1, B-flat major, op. 38 (Box 11)
    - Chamber music (Box 12)
      - Brahms, Johannes
        - Quintet, op. 34 (Box 12)
      - Grieg, Edvard
        - [Sonatas, violin & piano, op. 13, op. 14] (Box 12)
      - Haydn, Joseph
        - Quartet, no. 70, op. 76, no. 3, Edited by Reinhold Jockisch. (Box 12)
        - [Trios, violin & piano, no. 13-22] (Box 12)
      - Schubert, Franz
        - Quintet, C major, op. 163, Edited by Ferd. David. (Box 12)
      - Schumann, Robert
        - Klavierquartet, E-flat major, op. 47, Edited by Alfred Dörffel. (Box 12)
        - Quintet, E-flat major, op. 44 (Box 12)
      - Sinding, Christian
        - [Sonata, violin & piano, op. 27] (Box 12)
      - Smetana, Friedrich
        - [Trio, violin, violincello, & piano, op. 15], Arranged. by Richard Kleinmichel for piano, 4 hands. (Box 12)
    - Operas and opera excerpts (Piano-vocal scores) (Box 13)
      - Massenet, Jules
        - Cendrillon (Box 13)
      - Meyerbeer, Giacomo
        - L'Africana. O paradiso dall'onde uscito (Box 13)
      - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus
        - Don Giovanni (Box 13)
      - Parelli, Attilio
        - I dispettosi amanti, Note: I dispettosi amanti = A lovers' quarrel; Note: autographed. (Box 13)
      - Puccini, Giacomo
        - Madama Butterfly. Un bel di (Box 13)
      - Veracini, Francesco Maria
        - Rosalinda. A pastoral (Box 13)
      - Wagner, Richard
        - Das Rheingold (Box 13)
    - Other vocal music (Box 14)
      - Besly, Maurice
        - Music, when soft voices die (Box 14)
      - Charpentier, Gustave
        - Louise, a musical romance (Box 14)
      - Debussy, Claude
        - Il pleure dans ma coeur, Note: Il pleure dans ma coeur = It rains in my heart. (Box 14)
      - Fontenailles, H. de
        - Steadfast love (Obstination). (Box 14)
      - Foster, Stephen
        - Stephen Foster melodies, Arranged and inscribed by Martín Luis Guzmán. (Box 14)
      - Fourdrain, Felix
        - L'Oasis (Box 14)
      - Freer, Eleanor Everest
        - Rondel, op. 41, no. 10 (Box 14)
      - Pišek, Vincent (compiler)
        - Twenty Bohemian folk-songs, Note: autographed by J. E. S. Vojan. (Box 14)
      - Rimsy-Korsakoff, Nicolai
        - Chants nationaux russes (Box 14)
      - Saint-Saëns, Camille
        - Guitares et mandolines (Box 14)
    - Instructional materials (Box 14)
      - Cherubini, Luigi
        - Theorie des Contrapunktes und der Fuge (Box 14)
      - Zwintscher, Bruno
        - Musikalische Verzierungen. Practische Übungen und theoretische Erläuterungen. (Box 14)
      - [Unidentified]
        - [fragments] (Box 14)